啊，點樣？
選主席，選主席，你做麻薯啦。冇啊，Danny想啊嘛，Danny你係個呢個consultant，你接受主席，好冇嚇？有冇有冇啊？OK。
同埋我，我同謝偉智會多啲嘢問。
都係噉樣，但係不過同你多啲。
係，噉我哋進入誒議程嘅第二項，好唔好啊？
誒應該係有請。
冇見啊！
以前嘅第二項，我哋有請律師會嘅代表同埋administration政府嘅代表，好嘛？
係噉樣。
呢度個座位點喺度？
嗯。
佢哋講有冇paper要講，定係就咁講自己立場？
個關係。
bring us few個paper。
邊個paper？
佢要加減嗰啲咯，譬如佢點解要？
點解要噉樣講？
解釋下。
民族。
通常叫一啲標明。
Hi, Mr. Cohen.
Thank you for coming. If members don't mind, I would like to invite Mr. Cohen, Mr. Colin Cohen from the Law Society, to basically update us on the latest position regarding these rules and to to give us the Law Society's latest position on this matter. Thank you.
Mr. Chairman, first of all, I think there needs to be some apologies here for the extensive delay in respect of this matter, and mere culpa will come from our end in respect of this because the delay since last time we were here in 2005 has been a very, very long time.
The changes since 2005 as to what we're facing today are not very large. What we have done over the time is try to modernise and update these very very difficult rules, the accounts rules, which nobody likes. I mean, it's quite interesting. I examine accounts and every single student and every after.
我們都説，請廢除這個主題，因為它是個困難、複雜的問題。這些規則的目的是嘗試將一切納入一個部分的會計規則。之前，你必須到第A部分去，到實務指引，到這個指引，到那個指引。所以，現在你有在第V。
Accounts rules is one set of all the rules together.
We took on board the comments that were made to us last time we were here, in respect to the interest. But with great great respect, the interest provisions is one great big red herring, because with regard to the current rates of interest at zero zero zero one for V to have even, for example, I give you.
舉個例子，在我的律師行，這是一家中型、較大的律師行，位於香港，有16名律師。我們每一個月會在客户帳户裡存入約3500萬至4000萬港元。
The interest on that, I did a bit of research before I came here with my accountant. How much interest is due on that whole amount? Fifty five dollars last month, forty eight dollars the month before.
If we're going to try and get more than $500 on a four-day period, you're going to have to have over six billion Hong Kong dollars in your client's account to even get the $500 in that amount. So, at the moment, with interest rates being so low, I think all of this becomes a very academic issue per se.
Once interest rates ever get back to the five percent, and goodness knows when that will be, I think we are going to have to talk to the Americans about that. I don't see that happening for many, many years. Then the system we have in place now is clear, unequivocal. How it works out in respect of matters as well.
The other provisions here, I think, are just very straightforward. It's definitions more than anything else. I have to thank the DOJ who have been very, very helpful. I mean, fortunately, we in the law society, my technique on drafting isn't very good. They have been very, very helpful and have responded very, very efficiently to anything we've put to them. The problem.
Problem been over these years is that nobody really gave this matter the real attention it's needed. You put accounts on the back burner. It's not how could I say this is not the most, you know, pressing matter that happened. There's a change in the committees. I took over from the last chairman, Mr Michael Innes Smith. The consumer council set on matters. The chief justice, when he got the pre.
Chief Justice sat on matters, but I don't want to push the blame. Apologies, it should have taken that long period. Full stop. So.
I am delighted to go through in great detail these rules. I am delighted to take any questions people would have to ask. I mean, those solicitors here, I am sure, are very familiar. I used to examine them. I think, if I remember, when they were at Hong Kong University, and I still examine on this subject. So I'll be able to take up any questions on any matters as well. I hope I've given a bird's eye view, Mr. Chairman. Unless you want me to say anything further.
Thank you, Mr. Cohen。誒，不如咁啦，我誒請咗律政司嘅代表去發言先，跟住我睇下委員有啲乜嘢嘅問題，咁跟住我再處理嗰個嗰個誒條例本身啦，好唔好啊？阿黃生。
Is there a translation service? Nothing's coming through to me, so it's a bit unfair. Why don't we do this in English first? I would prefer that if we could do that.
If that's okay, Mr. Wong, would you mind doing your your representation in English? No problem. Thank you. Yeah, just just I'd like to thank Law Society for for the clarification about the OJ's role in this matter because. Hi, my, hi, my.
有冇麥啊？你啊，阿德，你或者埋少少，thank you，應該可以，係。
咁或者我用翻中文嚟表達喺呢個。
好多謝主席。誒，首先我想多謝翻律誒律師會方面係澄清翻我哋誒律政司嘅角色，因為的確今次嗰個一套嘅規例本身咧，其實就係由誒律師會個理事會本身係即係制定嘅。咁當然亦都經過即係誒。
啊！
首席法官嗰邊嘅同意噉，所以我哋喺當中其實個角色係盡量希望配合同埋支持，希望能夠做好個功夫。咁但係由於個角色問題，令到我哋睇到咧，我哋係一方面我哋會畀一啲觀察一啲啊comments啊，有一啲即係評論，但係最後究竟成個文件點樣處理或者個草擬啊？
表達背後嘅政策同埋內容咧，其實個角色都係喺啊律師會嗰邊嘅。咁呢度並不代表我哋係某一個角色喺度，我哋淨係想喺呢個機會，主席係啊將呢個啊分工係能夠清晰化。咁所以，如果有一啲關於闊啲嘅法律政策嘅問題，我哋都好樂意去表達意見。實際上喺手路上，我都有一個問題就。
關於嗰個涉及到利息嗰計算嗰度，都想作出詢問。不過我諗可以喺稍後一個階段當睇一啲具體嘅細節時候再表達。咁但係我哋想即係重申，我哋都係喺以往嚟講，一如以往，我哋係即係誒盡量配合呢啲誒規則嘅制定。喺我哋都係喺盡早嘅時間咧作出回應。咁好開心見到啊，Mr. Colin佢喺今日。
嘅表述上高，亦都係澄清咗呢點。多謝主席。多謝黃生。
啊，或者我畀機會委員啊，睇下初步有咩問題先，好冇？
暫時未有，咁不如我有請啊啊法律顧問咧。
幫我哋去。
睇一次，即係因為因為因為你可能最清楚，而家雙方誒而家暫時係呢個階段有啲乜嘢係未達成共識嘅，或者你可以誒帶我哋行一次好嗎？
咁個出發點啦，大家誒最好就拎住秘書處嗰邊準備嘅標明文本啦。
誒L誒L N一五一。
咁或者可以誒請誒律師公會嗰邊咧，得唔得？大家有冇L N一五一呢個文件喺手？
有，係啦。噉我哋嘅誒標明文本咧就係誒左手邊咧就係誒現行嘅條文嚟嘅，右手邊咧就係呢次而以加入或者誒修訂嘅條文。咁或者請誒誒誒律師會、律師公會嗰邊誒。
跟住個標明文本誒向誒委員解釋咧，就係點解？譬如有有噉樣樣嘅作出嘅修訂，點解想加？點解想改？好簡單咁介紹一次。噉我喺到適當嘅位誒位置咧，我就會將雙方面誒有誒。
有唔同意嘅地方咧，或者向律師會嗰邊誒提出嘅問題嘅。
一五一零。
係誒文件編號係C B四一三九誒stroke十二十三零五。
嗯。
誒係啦，譬如喺誒零零一頁嗰度咧，誒議議嘅第即係第一版咧，係係想加入議議第一A條原則嗰度嘅，或者請個施工會嗰度解釋點解要加入原則。
陳總，對。
Yes, for the reason why—I mean, the reason why we did all of this is for many reasons. First of all, we looked at other very similar legislation in other jurisdictions.
To help members, and the object of all of this is that if you are, let's say, a
在香港，正如您所知，你可以開辦實習後兩年。所以，你係新晉資深律師，經過兩年，你成為合夥人。你想要有某啲非常非常清晰嘅規則，去説明啲規則係咩。所以，一A係基本上係將啲定義同啲原則，作為維持你哋嘅錢嘅基礎。
Separate from office money. It is very, very straightforward. I mean, it basically says that how does one run one solicitor's accounts? To run one solicitor's accounts, one starts with basic principles, and the basic principle is the holy grail of solicitor's accounts: Thou shalt not use clients' money other than for clients' purposes.
And you got to have it all set up in such a way that is clearly identified and dealt with. The reason for having all these particular definitions, and I presume you want me to go for all of this, is to basically say that in the event of trouble happening, and in the event of the occasional bad apple, then.
We got to rectify matters. We can make it clear that you know from the very beginning what you do with regard to the principles of keeping your money separate. So you can see little A through little J makes it very, very clear as to what you want to do. And I, for an our point of view, was to make sure that the members of the law society who have to
Have your bookkeeping computer or otherwise have these clearly set out. So that deals with 1A and the principles in respect of other matters as well.
I think that's a very very good way of dealing with it. Most other jurisdictions deal with it, and it makes it easy for the solicitors to know what they're doing.
誒或者誒律師公會可以解釋下，而以第一A條係誒現在嘅practice directions裡面有冇嘅咧，定係完全係新嘅咧？
一，一。
reflected some existing rules. For example, in rule one A.
小A，它 refers to the solicitor practice rules。For example, in little J，the deliver annual accountants report it reflects the section section eight of the legal practitioners ordinance。
Let me help out. I think if you remember what I said at the very beginning here, you asked me why we're doing this.
As I said beforehand, you had practice rules, accounts rules, indemnity rules, all over the place.
We wanted to put into one document the fundamentals of the solicitors' account rules. Well, let me put the question to you: What's wrong with it doing it this way?
I think I'm a bit confused here because, as I said at the beginning, I don't think. I mean, I'm saying to you, I thought we can all read, we can all think, we can all go through this very clearly. You know, solicitor must do A, B, C, D, J. All of this is fundamental.
Either it was in the rules previously, either it's good common sense, and it was taken from some other matters which I looked at the English rules, the Australian rules, and we said, oh yeah, this looks quite a good idea to put this at the very beginning, and it makes a lot of common sense for people. So you have something at the very beginning which tells a solicitor how important it is to keep your client.
Money separate from your office money. So unless we can be, could we be more particular as to specific areas in which you have a gripe with, and I can answer those specific areas, which makes it far more better for me to come here and try to help you out with that. These are just principles, and principles are principles. So if you have an issue with this, tell me what the issue is, and I
我可以address each one. Don't want it sound to be difficult, but I am very very busy at the moment. Yeah, thank you, Mr. Cole.
Because there is no.
Perhaps you could do this in English. It's easier for me to hear it in English from you. No information note has been provided to us. So in order to assist members to understand which part of the proposed rule is new and which part are from existing practice directions, I just we just want information coming from.
from the policymaker as to to highlight the new parts to the members for them to consider. Okay, let me help you out with that.
A previous, B fundamental principle summarising, C if I recollect is summary, was wasn't before, D summary before.
E general summary, F general summary, G practice direction, K practice direction.
I general summary. J previous council rules. Thank you. It seems pretty fundamental and understandable to me. So unless members have any questions, we'll move on to the next item. Thank you.
So you want me to go through the interpretation? No, it's okay. We'll we'll we'll let the legal adviser handle this. Unless there is anything, we'll ask for your assistance. I think that's far better and far more efficient. So I can just answer your questions as to what's. That's the way we're going to do it. And we did write quite a long letter, if I recollect, in respect of all of this, and saying yeah, we do accept certain things, giving our views.
If we turn to page two of the markup version.
proposed.
amendment to rule two.
the the first line, we see a
Term a current or deposit account.
It is noted that here the rendition for deposit account is儲蓄户口，which is the same as the rendition for savings account，also儲蓄户口。
An enquiry has been made with the law society as to whether different words should be used.
and and I noted from the banking ordinance that the rendition for deposit account is存款户口，而as the rendition for savings account is儲蓄户口，and um would the law society please reconsider um whether
That it would be consistent with the existing law to adopt different term for deposit account and savings account.
真係呢啲噉樣嘅嘢咧，有幾？
都多嘅，因為佢全部我哋raise咗畀佢咧，佢都。
嗯。
Where's the answer to it?
Well, I've just been informed by Miss Wong, the legal adviser, that.
similar nature of queries, there are about 10 to 15 of them. Now, I think it will be a quite a time.
not a very efficient use of time if we are all to sit here and go through them one by one. Now the Law Society, correct me if I'm wrong, has been provided with the list of these queries.
啊！
So all we need from you, really, is. Month of November, we wrote a nice letter which I saw trying to answer all of these. Have you seen my letter or our letter? And I think we've answered them all. I mean.
Frankly speaking, if you want to come up with a better wording, which you think is going to be, I mean.
Splitting hairs, you know, it's not going to get anywhere. You know, I mean, this is why this matter is being delayed, delayed, delayed, delayed. I mean, I think in the end of the day, I'm quite happy to put to put in it whatever is going to be easier for the normal person to understand. We're talking about, you know, the working part is considered not necessary to make any change on the first one, but
你知，如果你諗，如果某人作為DOJ，或某人諗，它會幫助成員律師或成員公眾，噉，由，你知，我意思係，佢睇起來係一件好明顯嘅問題，即係咩係現金、存款或活期賬户。問題係，你放錢喺銀行賬户，通常係活期賬户，因為你喺度可以賺利息。
has to be a bank in Hong Kong. So, so any ideas of it not being a bank in Hong Kong, it's covered later on in the rule. Says it must be a bank in Hong Kong, but you know.
I mean, I'm open to any views and respect to this if it's valid. I think we answered that saying, well, we don't think it is that necessary. But you know, you know, if you want to.
Change it if it's in the best interest of the public by all means. I don't think it is. I think the rules are clear.
Let me clarify.
作為legal adviser to this subcommittee，我已經寫出我的觀察，在我的信給律師公會，他們基本上回覆我。
嗯，心口誒。
not answering our questions or not accepting our recommendations, and there are some obvious.
and there are some places where the Chinese and the English text of the proposed amendments or the proposed law.
have different meanings.
So that's why I I take the time to bring it to members' attention, and either the and it depends whether the law society will take it on, and I can see the difficulty because Mr. Colin doesn't understand Chinese, and a lot of it this is on the
Rendition of the Chinese text and the English text. The answer to all of this very very simple. Those just below me, I trust them implicitly. The DOJ, they're the experts on getting sure the translation is correct and dealt with, and I know they're very very helpful. Perhaps because they've come back with some comments saying they don't think they don't think they're too worried about it, but surely the
Best people to make sure there's no. I agree with you entirely. There mustn't be any difference between the translations. And I can't, you know, I mean, I I can't deal with that myself. Thank you, Mr. Cohen. Just one second. Anything from the Department of Justice on this? Thank you, Chairman. Again, we would like to clarify our position. Yes. The law is not.
社會事務諮詢委員會是實際上係製訂這個草案的，我們已經提交了我們的意見。我認為，立法會的立法委員已經提交了他們的意見。我認為，立法會的立法委員已經提交了他們的意見。
This definition of the meaning of deposit account or savings account, I note the exchange between the parties, and we we believe that this is something which the law society could maintain their view rather than following the suggestions from the from.
The legal adviser, but I noted from their response. In fact, there are a couple of places where the Law Society is prepared to amend the draft. For example, at page four of their letter of the seventh.
Of November and page five, there are two places, two two items which the law society consider appropriate to amend the draft rules, and of course, ultimately, if members here feels that there's a need to
make further changes is really open to members, but on my part, I think there are some issues I like to make it quite clear are really well.
within the discretion of the law society council, we do not have a strong view either way. So, but if, for example, chairman feels that the suggestions could be further considered by law society council, we will be happy to provide further input to the law society council so that perhaps some amicable amicable arrangement.
安排能可達成對技術性譯文。
Because well, sometimes we we we do not feel that they they must be amended. But I think sometimes perhaps so you don't have a firm view either way on many of these amendments. Can I take it on most of those? We feel that there's no need to change them.
on specific issues on a few of those I can read from my colleagues' comment from the law drafting division because I come from the legal policy division looking at the law broader legal policy issues but on law drafting points I understand that my colleagues have passed their observations on a few places where well they they are open to changes but I think it's really up
到社會事務諮詢委員會， to make a final decision. Of course, subject to the subcommittee's power of amendment. Sure. Okay, so I I understand your position quite clearly. Thank you. Thank you. So in order to shorten the process, shall we just focus on
the the parts where there is not yet a consensus between the parties.
但having taken into account what was just been said by the Department of Justice that they don't have a firm view on most, if not all, of the issues raised.
SEN'S CHAIRMAN, perhaps to clarify that we would say that most of those points raised, but helpfully raised by the AOA, would not necessarily require amendments.
There may be a few points, a couple points, actually, that would be up to Law Society consider further, perhaps, whether to make those amendments. Unless Chairman would like me to go into details, but I think Law Society would be in a better place because they have considered, I understand, through their working party, so they have taken into account our comments, our law drafting colleagues' comments.
before responding on the seventh.
Okay, thank you.
So, Miss Wong, what she will do now is to just go to those few more difficult or controversial ones, if I may put it that way, and and to cut out to cut short the process. Is that is that okay with members? Thank you, Miss Wong.
O O O Seven of。
We're looking at.
the same.
paper。
我 wish members to look at the Chinese text.
O O O Seven。
L L N one，呃，is still on。
誒one five one。
L.N. one five one. The rule is rule nine on exceptions.
If you just read the proposed amendment to Rule Nine,
Bracket two C small letter one。
嗯，The Chinese part.
It is not readily comprehensible. When I read it out in Chinese.
係，已有一份事務費單或關於事務費款額的其他書面告知交付。
如果呢度咧，大家唔睇英文嘅話咧，就咁睇呢句咧，其實係睇唔到。其實律師公會想講嘅意思啊，律律師公會嘅李小姐，或者你幫唔幫到誒我哋去解答呢個問題啊？其其實咧，我哋喺封信度咧，十一月七號嗰封信咧。
我哋亦都答咗關於呢個烏拉C，誒烏拉二C一嗰個告知交付。
嗰個中文。
嘅逆法。
噉我哋係basic DOJ嘅advice咧，佢都認為係唔需要改咯。
係嗱，呢度係講緊，究竟講緊啲乜嘢嘢咧？係講緊係個律師將張單或者關於款額嘅一個文件交畀個客啊，定係其實你睇落去咧，其他書面告知交付，定係你叫個客講緊交付去畀錢？
嗱。
即係如果你唔睇英文咧，你係完全睇唔到個意思嘅。已將一份事務費單或關於事務費款額的其他書面告知交付。
你係咪叫緊個客去畀錢咧？
定係你話個律師拎住張單，或者拎住一個有銀碼嘅文件。
佢交畀個客咧。
我。
我都明白個字面上係咪有少少誒問題咧？個中文嗰度。
但個中文嗰度咧，佢有講已有一份事務費單或關於事務費款項的其他書面告知交付。咁呢個就係指嗰個事務費單。
係啦，譬如你睇誒書面，其實係一個我哋話係應應用詞嚟嘅，但係你係啦，誒，但係你呢度用咧其他書面，好似其他文件噉樣用法咯。
嚇，其他即係你。
你。
其實就咁睇係睇唔明嘅，即係你你可能你睇咗英文，你畀英文影響咗，但係如果你就咁第一次睇中文，唔睇英文嘅時候。
豬食。
或者誒係啦。
我知。
即係威震言體。
問講嗰部分係咪已經cross out咗嘅？即係而家delete咗嗰部分嘅裏邊，其中一句嚟㗎。
誒講緊係喺。
第零零零零七頁，唔係係零零零七頁右手邊嘅一羅馬數字一同二嗰嗰誒嗰個第一嗰個誒嗰句啊，後面嗰句啊，已有一份事務費單話關於你睇唔睇到啊？謝偉俊。O.K.嘅，嚇。
course.
has been delivered to opposing suggestions.
誒冇㗎，因為佢都唔會受嘅，佢本身佢哋自己係啦。
我以前。
係可進仁醫院，係。嗯，我好快咁諗，我就會覺得係以一個書面，我唔知咪書面方式定係點，係交付畀個客咯。交付係嗰個係係個動詞，係畀個客。
嗯，即係用一個書面。
即或者我唔知係咪書面用一個文件。
誒去畀個客咯，其實嘅意思就係。
係啊，本身。
以前規常性。
係。
仲有個鐘啦。
即係。
sorry，主席係咪我應該將嗰個交付擺上上面，已交付一份嘅咯。
現時律師已有巴拉巴拉，然後告知交付。你可以話已交付一份事務費單或關於事務費得唔得？
將個動，將嗰個。
That is Chinese. What is written here is not Chinese.
諗唔到。
李小姐，李小姐，你誒？
你覺得謝偉俊議員嘅意見，你能唔能夠接受？
我試過。
誒係咪話應該改做已交付一份事務費單？
Right.
或關於事務費款項的其他書面告知。
係啦，即係將個交付。
搬上去，易交款有一份。
呢個要慢慢翻去再諗，呢個要慢慢再翻去再諗。
黃先生。
因為一方面，當然我哋唔係畀法律意見，即係啊律師會嗰邊。但係如果譬如話，今次議員提出嘅意見，我哋可以稍後。如果譬如啊律師會覺得再同我哋啊攞啲我哋有啲觀察嘅話，我哋可可以樂意咁做。現階段我個觀察就係誒，如果中文嗰度修訂英文，好明顯，亦都要作出修訂，因為英英文。
has been delivered。咁所以可能真係要一拼，再諗一諗個表述係點係最適合。因為只要我啲同事提出嘅時候咧，其實係覺得係誒可以唔改動嘅。原因係點解就係中英文對照嘅時候咧，其實個意思係清晰。咁當然議員如果有意見係再再修訂，好樂意。
再諗。
嗱，咁啦，誒，大家聽咗聽咗議誒誒啊，謝偉俊議員嘅議員咧。
Is the money? It's when you're putting the money into your office account or your client's account. But Mr. Colon, I think we're we're not in difference over matters of principle. Rather, it is the use of the exact wording in Chinese that is causing the the problem. Can't there be a proper? I'm sure someone can translate it.
係啊！
I'm sure it can be done. It has or it will be done already. But I think we've heard the comments made by the honourable Mr Porcher and the legal adviser, and also the Department of Justice. Can I, sorry, can I put the ball back to the Law Society on this particular provision? Absolutely. I think what we
Can do is try to have a, you know, get this all sorted out by sensible corridors. It seems to me this should be done very, very quickly. Yeah, it's a mere, it's a mere format. It's a mere form twist of the the wording. So this one you've got. Yeah, absolutely. We have no problems with that. Yeah. Okay. So shall we move to the next controversial?
嗯。
嗯，the following one, proposed rule two A, on page seven.
if we look at the proposed
to a。
你會見到，律師必須。
do A, B, C.
and then if you look at small Roman two.
一些。
The solicitor must do this.
failing which the payment should be paid in the client account not later than the third working day following the receipt.
can the can the law society explain why if if something is made a mandatory requirement, a solicitor must do this, and there is a failing which
And on, and the failing word provision is followed by the word should.
So is the is it really a mandatory requirement in the first place?
Yes, Mr. Cohen. Yes, well, I mean, let's look at it very clearly. What you've got here, you've got a situation as a solicitor when a bad amount of money comes in, and it's let's say the client gives you a hundred thousand dollars, and of that hundred thousand dollars, oh, part of that is for counsel's fees.
You then have the decision as to where that money goes, and as you can see, you know if it includes a disbursement as well as a client's money, whether it's meant to be for a bit of both, you you then decide what it is. You then decide whether you can split it or whether you can do that. And if you can't, sometimes it goes into office, sometimes it goes into client. If there's any doubt, you put it into client.
within a period of time. The problem is why you need that is it may take some time. The reason why you put the four to five days are because everyone knows as solicitors sometimes there's uncertainty as to what exact that money consists of and what that money is for, and that's why that extra time is needed. It's as simple as that.
我明。
誒，委員有冇問題？
係何俊仁議員。
四到五days。
maybe too short。
Well, because the service may have to sort out.
the the relevant say finance or invoices before， so。
Well, you know, your point's a very good point. People on a committee raise that, and in the end, because of the comments that this is so important, it means you've got to turn to it within four to five days. Remember this: there is that saving rule whereby you know you make a mistake, you make a mistake other than clerical mistakes. You know, so you've got to have a time period.
And if you go any longer than that, four to five days working days, which is actually four to five working days, is taking you into more than an actual week. Actually, if you go over that, so yeah, that's not. It's a point that was raised, and in the end.
Like committees, you find you got people with different views, and we thought that was the best timing. If you feel that it should be a little bit longer, I don't quarrel too much if you want to change it to the fifth, to the sixth, or something like that. But you wouldn't want to go. I mean, I mean, Mr. Chair, both of you are very experienced solicitors. I think one knows the problem is this one is the client gives you the ex dog.
So you're not too sure. Well, some of it is for this thing, some is for that. And you've had that before in practice, I'm sure, Mr Chair, Mr. I mean, you know, you've had that problem many, many times. So we think that was the easiest way to work it out.
In reality, this is not going to happen because everybody just puts it straight into their client's account and then sorts it out later.
And that's what happens. Which you can do. You're never what you're here. There, you're not in the breach if you get it into the client's account. Okay. Even though put in the client's account. Correct, absolutely, and and really. The bill ready. Otherwise, you don't put it in the office account. Exactly, exactly. And and this idea of we put in these rules because they're there for the exceptions in respect.
所以，我認為
唔該，誒，所以。
所以是個legal advice，suggesting the word shell should be used instead of shoot。我我我，just thinking about the logic，because if something is made mandatory。
then the logical consequences.
That will be ascension following, or so you must do something. Otherwise, ascension. But now, what the law society is proposing is you must do this.
fail in which you should do something.
So it seems to. What's what's what's the what's the? Is it really a mandatory requirement? That's my question.
Because because we're giving you exceptions. What we're saying to you, you know, you determine what it is. You then decide whether it's going to go into the client's account or not the client's account. If you're not too sure, then you do this. So, the fundamental mandatory is the first step is to determine what that money is for. Once you've determined what it's for, then you deal with it in accordance to the
所以我唔係太sure whether getting close to splitting the hair a bit, but
I could, I don't think it's a real issue here, frankly. Because in legislation, we usually talk about what you may do, what you must do.
is is is uncommon to talk about what you should do. you what you should do is usually in a practice direction.
所以，我我。
Just, but it's a policy. Yeah, but the problem, the problem here is you got anticipated disbursements. You see, and and it's not crystal clear. So it gives the flexibility. You determine it if you're not then sure what it exactly is. Then you do with it. See, in practice, money comes flying in from clients. You know, you got a surveyors report to do.
You got costs on account. You've got councils' fees. Numerous things happen, and even going to pay your fee notes out of it as well. So, if it includes a disbursement as well as clients' money. So, for example, you know we want you to pay councils' fees, and they want you to put money on account of costs. So, I'm giving $100,000 of which so much is for councils' fees, and so much is on
Account for the future. Now you got a choice.
Of where you can do that as well, and that's how it works. And you know, it's not. It's really the crucial issue is to a a solicitor must then do A, B and C. Once you get to C, if that part is for a disbursement incurred but not yet paid, either pay that payment in the client's account or paid into the office account within.
That certain amount. So I think it does. It's a logical procedure that if you're a solicitor and you know how to deal with clients' money, you're a lot better now than you were before when it really wasn't a mess. What you should do with it as well. It's the nature of the beast. We're much easier. We simply change the word should to must then.
Third last.
Failing which the payment must be paid into the client account. Instead of failing which the payment should, we change it to failing which the payment must be paid into client account, not later than the fifth working day. I'm happy with that. That will be consistent with the logic. And the legal adviser will be happy with it. I hope.
Thank you, Mr. Chan. The law society is happy with me. I'm very happy to keep the legal adviser happy. Okay, well, so everyone's happy.
兩小點。係，we are talking about the the fourth working day and the fifth working day. and I think the proper rendition should be第四個鐘工作日、第五個工作日，not四個工作日、五個工作日。
即係中文嗰度加翻個弟字。
the fourth working day, the fifth working day.
係。
的第的第係嘛？係係，即係中文嗰度咧就加翻的第四個工作天的，跟住後邊的第五個工作天。阿李小姐有冇問先？如果唔係中意問，好麻煩嘅。
冇問題。O K，一一問要happy，我happy。O K，嗱咁即係英文同中文都O K啦，即係大家都能夠接受啦。
係嘛？
其他委員冇問題啊嘛？呢度好，噉我哋去第三個啊。
爭議點咧，好嗎？OK。
Let's turn to page nine of the markup version.
要唔要轉？
yeah。
oblig obligation to keep accounts, yep.
Its obligation to keep accounts.
Here we have sent a letter to the law society inquiring what.
the last the qualification modifies the qualification is that are necessary for the operation of a mechanical or computerised system of bookkeeping. What that phrase modifies?
And then the solicitor law society comes back to us, telling us that that phrase modifies such cards, other permanent documents, and the information stored in a computer and retrievable in a permanent and feasible form.
So this is the English text, but if you look at the Chinese text, it doesn't reflect what is what is what the English text said.
嗯。
你講緊邊個字唔對啊？誒。
中文嗰度，誒，佢將機械報記同埋電腦報記拆咗。
誒，即係如果你睇英文咧，佢係that's necessary for the operation of a mechanical or computerised um system of bookkeeping。嗯。咁但係中文咧，佢就將
誒。
機械報記系統。
就拆咗落去中間，跟住又將電腦報記系統拆咗落去。
令到誒。
個中英文。
唔對稱，完全唔係唔係嗰樣嗰嗰回事。
李小姐，你幫唔幫到手？
呢個我諗，我哋要問翻D.O.J嗰度咧個law drafting嗰個呢個，因為啲涉及到technical terms。
誒。
或者啊，黃生。
我瞭解，即係我哋誒草業科嘅同事就覺得現時嗰個誒表述咧係冇問題。咁但係如果譬如話誒誒法律顧問係有意見，我哋可以即係請。如果轉達咗誒律師會，我哋可以翻去再再大家再睇下有冇啲咩可以進一步點樣再。我我我能夠睇到。
點解誒阿黃法律顧問係有個有個有個問題喺度嘅？咁如果可以嘅話，麻煩誒誒律政司嘅同事或者law誒或者可以可唔可以畀一個畀一個好啲嘅版本我哋得唔得？誒，我哋可以同誒誒律師會嗰邊達。
大家即係即係配合啦，應該即係誒將頭先即係法律顧問提出嗰個關注點嗰度係另外一點咧，就係as the case may be。as the case may be咧，通常就係有幾個情況噉，跟住你就話as the case may be噉啊，擺喺尾嘅。但係而家你個用法就好奇怪咧，就係擺咗。
咁喺第三嗰個，你有一二三嘅，你擺喺第三嗰個項之前。
誒，其實嗰個咧得一個情況嘅，咁咧就係，你就話誒。
即係視乎情況，但係其實得一個情況，咁同埋其實亦都考慮翻有冇需要呢幾個字咯。
即係如果冇咗呢幾個字都得嘅，其實又冇需要。
即係as the case may be咧。
唔係咩？
ester case.
係啦，即係佢一係就hard copy，一係就即係佢其實而家我呢個係我tablet，其實tablet咗會容易睇咯，佢就擺咗喺呢度，其實通常係擺尾㗎嘛。
同埋有冇需要？
點解我會特別提到as the case may be咧？因為我同律師會嗰度誒就有個即係。
傾嘅過程裏面咧，佢就會講，亦需視乎情況，包括乜乜。
噉我就會提出咧個需其即視乎情況，其實唔係需咯。個需係係需當作包括誒shall be deemed to include，而唔係需視乎情況。
咁亦係。
Be is forwards, as the case may be. Would there be any difference if all these forwards are deleted? Can we just delete as the case may be? Is
Now my brain is racking as to how we got all of this, and I tell you why. I tell you why. Some people aren't very good at keeping their accounts.
And what they do is some firms who are sole proprietors, on the back of an envelope type of accounting.
And that's the reason maybe because you know people just do their records. They're not very good at doing it. But as a sole proprietor, they don't get any real advice and they create their account in a very vague way. So that was the answer why that was put in. But if you want to throw it out, I don't think it's going to cause me any problems. But it may cause people to be inexperienced. You know.
係。
Seven, you know, of the number of law firms in Hong Kong, most seventy percent sell propertors or you know partnerships, and they have a real problem in sometimes trying to get their accounts together. And some of them don't even do the accounts. We don't even deal with clients' money. Then all of a sudden they have clients' money. So that's why that word was put in there as well. As the case may be.
Can it go to the end of Route 10?
呃，是，C。
所以，我 put， as the case may be， at the very end of the third sub provision。
我 also want to read from a guide to styles and practices issued by the law drafting division of the DOJ. It says the expression as the case may be is often used unnecessarily in legal writing. Avoid it if, but if without it there can be ambiguity, consider recasting the provision.
So my question is: Is it necessary?
because we are talking about ten five.
水。
我found a case by be further out, didn't I?
真係幾好。
歷史。
係，我係。
而家咪睇緊。
I'm at the end. May work very well for me.
I think you can put it at the end. Actually, it'll have the same effect. Or as the case may be, at the very end, I'll be fine with that. It's what you do. Just put that. 好好。大家其他委員同意。
O.K.
yes，Miss Lee。
phrase as the case may be in Wu Ten Five。
put at the end of that subrule five， right？
Yes. Or my question is: Is it really necessary? Because even if you need it, it is usually put at the end of the sentence.
你你有 another case maybe in rule two or something.
my my my next question is is it really necessary, given the modern
trend of dropping.
但 if you look at Route Ten Sub Route Two,
The phrase, as the case may be, is in the middle, not at the end.
所以，That's why I think the OJ.
I mean, Mr Cohen has already said that they have. You're you're happy to put it. I'm happy to put anything in which fee makes it easier and understandable, which it makes it. It does seem to be. I think it's sufficiently clear now if it's placed at the very end. I can put this at the very end. I don't think it makes any difference what.
I don't think we need to debate about where exactly, but at the end is fine. Mr. Wong.
誒利用呢個機會都係澄清啦，因為我相信嗰個稿並非D.O.J整理嘅，因為係律師會嗰邊整理。我哋就係從一個即係整體同嗰個法律個草擬方面嗰個格式有冇出入作為一個審核嘅標準。所以我我諗，如果當話係誒噉樣係因為係誒律政司嗰邊整理，我諗我我係想代表啲同事係情。
整翻呢樣嘢，應該就明白。所以如果譬如話有有方法去提升嗰個草業，我哋係冇問題。係多謝你，王先生。
咁點講？
嗯，我 have。
This would work, from my quick review. Okay, thank thank you, Mr. I have I have one more question on this.
Rule five.
嗯，啦。
它 mention such cards. We're looking at the left hand side, section 10 sub rule 5. Yes, in this rule each of the expressions, 好嘛？ Yes, book, ledger and record. Yes, shall be deemed to include a loose leaf book and such cards or other permanent documents. Such cards, such
誒。
Usually, when when the cast have been raised for a second time, you use such. But here, cast is raised for the first time.
所以誒。
should should it be changed to any or or what? Such cast here is raised for the first time. Shall be deemed to include reduced. So to say, such cast is is.
So instead of such, we use any, and then we cancel. Do we use card or cards?
cards because it's an old-fashioned bookkeeping thing where people put little things on the cards and it's very very old-fashioned so that's why we have that. Okay, so can we change the word such to any, so it reads any such cards or other permanent jobs? Yes, absolutely. Okay, thank you, Mr. Cohen.
係。
仲有一個係咪啊？
我哋會唔會有其他方案？
unction of the word, with the phrase that are necessary for the operation of mechanical or computerised.
系統簿記。
是是connected with such。
因為如果 read the whole sentence together，such cards or other permanent documents，blah blah blah，and then come coming to the end。
That are necessary for the operation.
of a mechanical or computerised system of booking, so is the word such related to the?
this phrase，this clause。
Because I noted that the Chinese rendition they use Yamho. Oh, I see. Yeah. So and and because this is raised for the first time.
as long as it's clear.
Alright.
Going back to propose Rule 6A at page four of the markup version.
English and Chinese. English. English, page four.
6A.利息 on client account.啊， yes. Here, enquiry have been made with the law society on on the words used, and the words are interest earned and interest accrued. For interest earned, they use賺取的利息. Interest accrued, they use顯
衍生的利息。
and I was asking whether there is any difference in the term used, and they replied no. and I just wonder whether the law society would consider adopting a single word.
when there was really no difference in the meaning.
Mr. Cohen。
Translation, pass it over. I don't, I can't answer that to be honest. It's not only translation because it's accrued and earned and accrued. Well, yeah, well, accrued interest is interest which will accrue on the account as it builds up over time. Earned interest is a specific amount which you may get.
立即。
Interest earned is different from interest accrued, actually. So interest earned is the interest earned on the actual amount when you know that. The interest accrued is the rolling over paces as well. So this is why you know the rules. It's the English rules to me make a lot of sense, a lot of common sense. So you can translate it by all means.
But the crude and earned are slightly different because you're cruing it up all the time. That's one area. So it's interest upon interest. Earned is when you get the interest as well. But again, 0.0001% at the moment while while this is all suspended. It's academic. Yes. If that is the case, I will liaise with the law society on.
A consistent use of the word for interest earned and interest accrued for the Chinese, yes, fine. I'm very helpful. That'll be very, very helpful. 李小姐有冇補充？Very helpful to do that as well.
我有one more question。係，等等等，梁美芬議員係。
翻嚟咧就係話嗰個中文咧係咪用顯生咧，定係？
係咪積累？accumulate？
唔係一定係顯生嘅喎。
yeah，we are talking about the translation. I I I totally agree your explanation。衍生係咪derived啊？
啊，Yeah， accrue唔唔係翻譯做衍生，I I don't think so，應該係累積出嚟就accrue，Right？唔緊要，我哋derived呀，derived is the English word，所以可能可能中文嗰度誒，你中文執一執佢。
就應計利息啊！
誒，我查過誒字典咧，《A Glossary of Financial Terms》呢度係用咗誒誒大陸、誒香港同台灣嘅用語都有比較嘅。噉佢interest accrued咧，佢係用英計。
利息噉我亦都留意到法例裡面咧，如果interest accrue類似嘅情況咧，佢係用累算利息。嗯，因為我係啦，因為我諗誒普通市民睇衍生其實係唔睇唔到accrue嗰個意思，睇唔到嚇。
因為我哋雷曼成日衍生工具係講緊另，即係講緊另外一樣嘢。阿李小姐，O唔O K啊？明唔明白？
我明白嚇嚇，明白。噉我諗睇下一次過，我諗係誒legal個誒legal adviser會畀翻封信，我哋set out曬呢啲。
唔係嗱，唔需要咁複雜嘅，因為頭先我哋已經講咗，我哋同意同埋想修改啲咩啊。頭先委員同埋誒誒律政司嘅同事都已經講清楚㗎啦。噉我諗唔需要話又整一輪書信噉樣，因為噉樣嘥大家時間。不如咧，如果我建議能夠嘅話咧，就係誒我哋會後誒。
誒，你哋大家坐低去再講一次，因為因為已經其實其實頭先得三點啫嘛嚇，我我都記得係乜嘢，所以我諗唔需要再整書信啦，應該冇。
誒，仲有一點，仲有一點，係，仲有一點，嗯，誒，page four。
Ruleset say，誒on subparagraph three B。
here it mentions on receipt of the client's request for a certificate.
and and then the council must do something, and here I'm just asking for the time frame because it's um.
跌倉松。
must do something on receipt of the client's request. And here the rendition in Chinese is.
在接獲後。
and talks about a time frame.
is not.
在接獲時。
所以我 just wondering。
what is the time frame?
或，你 refering to
um a specific point of time or a period of time, because the use of how
is more refers to a a period of time rather than a specific point of time.
and I must mention that on an or in on another occasion in the same rule, when on receipt of is used, the rendition is交代獲悉。
translation.
係，係，係。
I think the issue is the council must investigate and it will investigate as it you know.
In the time frame, things fit. I mean, it's like many issues with the law council. Someone says you must, you know, in a disciplinary matter, the council must do this. It's not saying it must do it within one day, two days, three days. It must investigate, and in due course, it will issue its certificate. I don't think you're going to put in time periods for the council. We must do it within so many.
day so many days so many days, it's rather like in one of the disciplinary proceedings, you you may if you you must do A B and C, you know you do it.
That's how I look at it.
我部咧比冇。
accurate，accurate to say after after receipt of。
Because on seems to point to a point a specific point of time.
I mean, that sounds to make a lot of sense. After after receipt, it it it will do that. Okay.
解決咗我問題。seems seems acceptable to me and members，我都係問同一個問題。因為因為呀，because I think we need to give time to the council。yeah， I mean you can't。yeah， you can't say as when as at they upon receipt。yeah， upon receipt。啊，咁中文使唔使改啊？
誒，佢中文而家已經係在接獲後㗎啦。哦，咁after receipt會準啲。係。
O.K.，咁大家同意就得。
係。
誒係咁多。
After a seat, that's fine.
誒。
一五一係咁多啦。係，誒，That's it for one five one。
Four, so we move on to one five two.
係。
一五二。
Again, we only focus on the really controversial parts, and for the other parts, we heard Mr. Wong said that the DOJ is doesn't have any issue with any particular bit.
of the proposed rules, and we'll take it that the government is happy with it. And unless the law society wishes to change it, we'll leave it as it is. But subject to what Miss Wong, the legal adviser, has to say. Okay? Yes.
on page one of LN one five two, my only enquiry is on the use of儲蓄帳户for deposit account when that word is already used for as the rendition for savings account.
and I would ask the law society to consider using.
啊！存款賬户。
as in the banking ordinance.
我哋睇緊一五二嘅中文版。
嘅第二段嗰個啊！
第幾行？誒，under client account，係啦。
用儲蓄帳户。
你就可以。
應該存款帳，應該存款賬户。
儲蓄同存款。
儲蓄同。
嗯。
律師公會話。
要開個 normal bank account，因為
Look at it carefully. Client account means.
It's a current current council deposit account.
用唔用銀行 account？
I mean, the English looks good to me. I can make no comments on the Chinese translation.
李小姐，但係誒。
儲蓄帳户個。
嗰個係咪廣闊一啲咧？因為如果存就用存款賬户，好似淨係擺入去。
誒。
你説明 to me to us in your letter that deposit account is wider than saving account, but since there are two words deposit account and saving account in the rules, um.
maybe we should also use two words for.
the rendition，just as in the banking ordinance，they also use two different Chinese words for deposit account and savings account。
所以，我問，maybe we should achieve consistency.
點解係存款賬户？存款賬户，我我明白喎，李小姐，存款賬户係比較比較闊少少喎，呢個呢個字眼係能夠概括誒多唔同類型嘅嘅嘅嘅賬户，多個多個就咁儲蓄喎，因為儲蓄就係淨係saving啫嘛。
係。
呢個High Court Ordinance都係啲，明白，明白。
即係即係律師會冇問題係咪？嚇可以改委員有冇問題？
O.K.
係啦，改中文嗰個由儲蓄帳户改成存誒存款帳户，噉就比較闊少少。
咁一五三。
最後。
係，我知。
I just like to know what is the.
sticking to the meaning of client account only to accounts.
Located in a bank in Hong Kong.
reason for that is when it comes to disciplinary matters.
We've had real, real problems with people putting their clients' account out of Hong Kong. When we come to intervene or deal with matters, you cannot get the information, nor can we get control of the bank. For example, I've been appointed intervention agent on many occasions. The real problem is getting in and getting control of the bank accounts. Could you imagine trying to get into control of bank?
accounts in BVI's in other countries as well, and we wouldn't have any ability to control or look after the clients' monies in the event of intervention. So the main objective is to keep the bank accounts in Hong Kong to protect the people of the public of the metropolis of Hong Kong. As simple as that.
So, so the legal consequence of this rule is that a solicitor firm shall not deposit clients' money in overseas account. Correct. So, they need to. Yes, absolutely. Because when we, I mean, when we come for difficulties, when we have to intervene, as you've seen, and it's been coming quite a few recently, and I've become an intervention agent.
I have enough trouble getting an order from a Hong Kong court to get control of it. So can you imagine trying to get a control of a bank account and if in BVI and if somebody got smart and put it in some weird place, we could get no money out of it. We could be left chasing our arms for a long, long time. So that's why we changed the rules for that. But there is a waiver provision in Rule Fifteen. Yes.
How is he going to do? Well, for waivers, like anything for waivers of rules, like for the accounts, you've got to come with a very, very good reason to waive, and it's up to the council to consider waiving things in respect to matters. So it has to be dealt with on application. On application for waivers for everything, it's quite common in all the other rules.
So in other words, the solicitor cannot shall not deposit clients' money in an overseas account even on clients' instructions. Yes, correct, absolutely. Unless there is a waiver. Unless there's a waiver, and the chance of that being given, I think will be won't be ever be given. I can't see that happening.
And that becomes the reason why that came in is that I I made sure that came in because when I did an intervention, people lost their money and we couldn't get the money because the account was in the middle, really in the middle of where was it? Spain.
你知道，係真係某啲非常愚蠢嘅嘢。然後你試過想控制銀行賬户喺西班牙，所以啲人話：，為咩會發生呢？，因為我哋唔控制我哋嘅成員，所以就係噉。但係喺實施呢個規則之前，蘇利斯特可以做嘅嘢，可以嗎？可以。可以
But there's been some. We changed. We no, we did a practice direction out saying they can't. Correct.
Yeah, before the change was ambiguity in respect of all of this, but we've made it very clear. I think there was a practice direction that came out saying that you can't do it, so you're in breach of the practice direction. I see. I think a practice direction came out some time, but we need to get this into the rules to stop this happening. And this is quite an important one, which you know, yeah, we need to do.
Thank you.
I understand from Ms. Wong. Thank you very much, Ms. Wong. That we have come to an end of the controversial issues, so there are no more. And given what the DOJ has said that the Law Society proposed amendments to the rules are all acceptable.
save for the four points which we've just discussed, and which you have agreed to go away and amend. Now let me consult with the secretary to see how we could do it, because there are some time limitations.
視乎委員會覺唔覺得啊？主席視乎委員會覺唔覺得有需要再開一次會，係睇翻誒嗰啲嘅修訂。如果係誒大家係覺得誒可以先係誒傳越先嚇，咁傳越咗之後，或者誒如果有委員覺得有需要係開會先至安排會議都得。咁但係因為我。
我哋嗰個審議期咧係誒係係好問㗎啦，噉就已經係延展咗，噉係去到誒十月五號，噉我哋咧即係話要喺十一月二十三號咧就要向內會係提交報告㗎啦，咁而議員提出誒誒修訂嘅預告期咧，最遲係十一月二十八號嘅。
嚇，噉我哋誒，如果係需要開會，即係話咧，盡最好咧，就係喺十一月二十三號之前誒開會嚇。
主席啊！主席，係唔好即係我諗傳譯咧，一整番嘢好簡單，同埋都好技術性。係啊，係啊。如果大家同意咧，你傳譯，我哋大家冇問題，噉就唔好開會啦。咁其他委員有冇意見？
嚇唔使再開會啦，噉我哋就咁傳閲啦。噉就麻煩律師會咧，係將嗰個頭先我哋同意咗改嗰啲修訂咧，就畀一畀秘書處。噉我哋就傳閲嚇。咁如果委員冇意見咧，我哋就可以誒唔需要再開會啦，就可以我係咪要做個博？係啦，誒向內。
會做一個報告嚇，就話已經係冇其他嘅誒意見同收。Do this very very quickly. Um, what we've said, we've drafted the amendments just in right now, so it will take hopefully within the next 24 hours we can get something out. I think Andrew's looking very strongly at me now, a little bit longer than that. You just ruin her next few days. No no no no no, I haven't, because we got like we're over.
I got overseas lawyers qualifying examination tomorrow, so I got to get this done before I have to start. I think it's in the interest of everyone that Law Society really come up with the agreed amendments within the next few days, so that we could circulate within the members and the subcommittee, and then we'll hopefully pass it without further comments and objections.
And now.
Thank you, Miss Lang.
嗯。
冇其他嘢。
我講。
Oh, Mr. Cohen. Yes. I've just been reminded by the secretariat that please provide both English and Chinese versions when you give us the amendments that has been agreed on just now.
O.K.
Yeah, thank you.
手做工廠，你全部。
And also, and Miss Wong has suggested that you provide an information note explaining.
But look for for future references, so that we could save some time. Instead of asking you these questions here, we would know in advance the meaning behind your your suggested proposals. Thank you.
We take on board those comments. We'll do.
有冇？
其他委員有冇問題？冇。OK，散會。